Benjamin Tallmadge Collection
Litchfield Historical Society
- Correspondence, 1776-1856
  - 1820 Mar-Jul (Folder 51)
    Four letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. The letters discuss primarily financial business, including Tallmadge's suit against Samuel Brown and his desire for Cushman to sell some property for him. Elsewhere, Tallmadge also mentions ripening plums and a canker sickness among the children.
  - 1820 Aug-Oct (Folder 52)
    Four letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman and Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, which primarily discuss financial matters, including the suit against Samuel Brown and the purchase of a mortgage. He also mentions the arrival of his son George Washington Tallmadge on furlough from West Point.
    To his daughter Maria, Tallmadge also writes concerning his desire to leave land in Ohio to his children, and reports on the death of Lyman Beecher's child and other social and family news.
  - 1820 Nov-Dec (Folder 53)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. In the first letters, he discusses politics, including his prediction of James Monroe for President; as well as financial matters. He also writes about a fire which consumed the home of Samuel Plumb.
    In the second letter, Tallmadge reports on the conclusion of his suit against Samuel Brown and advises Cushman on building rather than renting his home.
  - 1821 Jan-Apr (Folder 54)
    Two letters, one from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge, and the other from Tallmadge to Cushman. Cushman's letter primarily discusses political matters, while Tallmadge's letter asks Cushman to invest some of Judge Tapping Reeve's money and discusses Cushman's impending visit to Litchfield.
  - 1821 May-Jun (Folder 55)
    Three letters to John Paine Cushman, two from Benjamin Tallmadge and one from Tapping Reeve. Tallmadge's letters report on the arrival of Cushman's wife and children at Litchfield and discuss financial matters. Reeve's letter asks Cushman to invest his money for him.
  - 1821 Jul-Sep (Folder 56)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman and John Paine Cushman. To his daughter Maria, Tallmadge writes of his intention to leave money for his grandchildren. To Cushman, Tallmadge discusses the stocks and capital of the Commission Company.
  - 1821 Oct-Dec (Folder 57)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. The letters report family news, including the travels of Cushman's mother; Tallmadge's concern that his children will not be properly converted and his approval of the religious revival; and his daughter Harriot's recent wedding. Tallmadge also writes about the financial details of the Commission Company.
  - 1822 Jan-Mar (Folder 58)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. Tallmadge refers to a controversy between Judge James Gould and Judge Tapping Reeve; discusses the sale of Cushman's Ohio lands and his own stock; and praises the religious revival in Litchfield. The last letter includes a note by Maria Tallmadge to Tallmadge's daughter Maria with social news.
  - 1822 Apr (Folder 59)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman. Tallmadge reports the religious conversion of the family of Stephen and Roxana Clark; the recent illness of the revivalist preacher Asahel Nettleton; and his pleasure at Maria's own religious fervor. He also provides extensive religious reflections.
  - 1822 May-Jul (Folder 60)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. He reports on the extreme illness of Mrs. Deming; the conversion of Helen Peck on her deathbed; and the deaths and illnesses of other friends and family members. Also included is a receipt by Tapping Reeve for money deposited with Cushman.
    One of the letters also contains a note to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman by Tallmadge's wife, Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge. The note is accompanied by a poem, copied by Sarah Hallett, on Helen Peck's death.
  - 1822 Aug-Dec (Folder 61)
    Three letters to John Paine Cushman, two from Benjamin Tallmadge and one from Felix Tracy. The letters discuss the illness of Mrs. Tibbits; the appearance of yellow fever in New York; Tallmadge's recent trip to New Haven where he attended a religious meeting and witnessed the ordination of three missionaries; and the death of his son William.
    The letter from Tracy updates Cushman on the financial state of Tallmadge's property.
  - 1823 Jan-Feb (Folder 62)
    Letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman and Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, reporting the death of Tallmadge's brother.
  - 1823 Mar (Folder 63)
    Four letters to John Paine Cushman, three from Benjamin Tallmadge and one from Phebe Tallmadge.
    Benjamin Tallmadge writes concerning his investments; the legacy of his recently deceased brother John; and his thoughts on religion, including the rebirth of the soul and the subjects of a sermon by Lyman Beecher. He also reviews the availability of boarding places for young ladies who wish to attend the Litchfield Female Academy.
    The letter from Phebe Tallmadge describes the death and funeral of Uncle John Tallmadge, Benjamin Tallmadge's brother.
  - 1823 Apr (Folder 64)
    Letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman, reporting on Lyman Beecher's departure for Boston, the religious revival, and the possibility of students of the Litchfield Female Academy boarding with the Buel family.
  - 1823 May (Folder 65)
    Five letters, four from Benjamin Talllmadge to John Paine Cushman and one from Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman. Tallmadge discusses financial matters; compliments Cushman on his tax law; confirms the engagement of lodgings for students at the Litchfield Female Academy; and reports on the marriage of Phebe Tallmadge to the Rev. Mr. Mason of Washington. He also mentions Lyman Beecher's successful sermons in Boston.
    The letter from Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge reports on social and family news and discusses fashion in apparel and home decorating.
  - 1823 Jun-Sep (Folder 66)
    Five letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman and Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman. He reports on his wife's ill health and the remedies she has tried, expresses regret that he cannot travel to Troy due to his wife's illness, and discusses financial matters, including the signing of new bonds.
  - 1823 Oct (Folder 67)
    Three letters to John Paine Cushman, two from Benjamin Tallmadge and one from Elizabeth Reeve. Tallmadge's letters report social news and plan his visit to Troy to see Cushman.
    Reeve's letter describes her own and her husband's failing health and urges Cushman to take care with the money he has invested for the Reeves, as it may soon be the only sustenance of the fatherless boy, Burr, whom she and her husband had adopted.
  - 1823 Nov-Dec (Folder 68)
    Letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, which describes his ill health and moderate recovery, and his recent fall from his horse.
  - 1824 Jan-Feb (Folder 69)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman and John Paine Cushman. Tallmadge provides a detailed description of his recent illness, and discusses his intention to leave land in Ohio to his children. He also discusses financial affairs, including Tapping Reeve's will and investment with Cushman, as well as provides religious reflections.
  - 1824 Mar (Folder 70)
    Five letters, from Lucius Smith to Benjamin Tallmadge and from Tallmadge to Smith; and from Tallmadge and Benjamin Tallmadge Jr. to Cushman.
    The letters between Tallmadge and Smith concern a financial dispute. To Cushman, the Tallmadges relate social and financial news; Tallmadge Sr. also remarks on his feelings at recollecting scenes from the Revolutionary War.
    The last letter is appended by a note from Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, relating social and family news.
  - 1824 Apr-Jun (Folder 71)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman, which discuss the financial aspects of Tapping Reeve's will; the illness of Cushman's father; and his own illness and thoughts on death.
  - 1824 Jul (Folder 72)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman and Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, sharing family news and consoling them on the loss of their daughter, Maria Hallet Cushman.
  - 1824 Aug (Folder 73)
    Six letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman and Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman. He consoles the Cushmans on the death of their daughter Maria Hallet; writes about his ideas concerning the spiritual significance of mourning; and his concerns for the health of another of their children, Tallmadge Cushman. He also mentions the imminent arrival of Marquis de Lafayette in Hartford.
  - 1827 (Folder 74)
    Five letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman, which comment on the ecclesiastical trial against Nathan Beman for charges against his method of conducting revivals by Lyman Beecher and Asahel Nettleton. He also discusses upcoming visits by his children, family and social news, and business affairs.
  - 1828 Jan-Feb (Folder 75)
    Three letters, between John Paine Cushman and Benjamin Tallmadge, discussing business affairs and Tallmadge's concern over his daughter Harriot's ill health.
  - 1828 Mar-Apr (Folder 76)
    Three letters, from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge, discussing financial matters. One letter includes an enclosed business letter from Aldis Davis about rents from land in Vermont.
  - 1828 May-Jun (Folder 77)
    Four letters, between John Paine Cushman and Benjamin Tallmadge, containing financial matters; news of family, friends; and comments on the religious revival.
  - 1828 Jul-Aug (Folder 78)
    Three letters, from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge, containing financial matters, including mortgages and real estate; as well as family news.
  - 1828 Sep-Dec (Folder 79)
    Three letters: two between Benjamin Tallmadge and Charles Perkins; and one from John Paine Cushman to Tallmadge.
    The letters between Tallmadge and Perkins discuss a financial and legal arrangement. The letter from Cushman discusses other financial matters and provides an update on the revivalist preacher Nathan Beman.
  - 1829 Jan-Feb (Folder 80)
    Two letters, between Benjamin Tallmadge and John Paine Cushman, discussing a failed loan to Mssrs. Stone and Filley as well as a loan to Mr. Clapp.
  - 1829 Mar-Dec (Folder 81)
    Two letters: one from Elizabeth Reeve, Tapping Reeve's widow, to the Cushmans; and one from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge.
    Mrs. Reeve writes of the death of her child and offers religious reflections. Cushman writes to discuss financial matters and to report that Nathan Beman has decided to stay in Troy.
  - 1830 Jan-Jun (Folder 82)
    Letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman offering religious reflections.
    Also in the folder is a legal document, signed by five of Tallmadge's children, waiving their rights to money from their father so that it can be paid towards their brother George Washington Tallmadge's debts. The document is accompanied by a request by Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman to comply with his children's request.
  - 1830 Jul-Dec (Folder 83)
    Two letters: one from Benjamin Tallmadge, Jr. to John Paine Cushman; and one from Benjamin Tallmadge, Sr. to Martin Clapp. Tallmadge, Jr.'s letter refers to a financial transaction for carpeting and mentions his future travels.
    Tallmadge, Sr.'s letter to Clapp expresses his disappointment that Clapp has been so delinquent on his interest payments, and informs him he has transferred Clapp's debt to his children.
  - 1831 Jan-Feb (Folder 84)
    Six letters, between John Paine Cushman and Benjamin Tallmadge, discussing Tallmadge's illness; the religious revival in New York and elsewhere; and financial matters.
  - 1831 Mar-Dec (Folder 85)
    Three letters, between Benjamin Tallmadge and the Cushmans, which discuss financial matters; the ill health of Tallmadge's wife, Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge; and the religious revival.
  - 1832 Jan-Feb (Folder 86)
    Letter, from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge, discussing financial matters related to the death of Benjamin Tallmadge, Jr.
  - 1832 Mar (Folder 87)
    Four letters: three between Benjamin Tallmadge and John Paine Cushman, and one from Tallmadge to Martin Clapp.
    The letters between Tallmadge and Cushman discuss financial matters. One letter, marked "private," grants Cushman power of attorney over Tallmadge's funds.
    The letter to Clapp contests Clapp's claim of usury against Tallmadge.
  - 1832 Apr-May (Folder 88)
    Three letters, between Benjamin Tallmadge and John Paine Cushman, discussing financial affairs, including Martin Clapp's suit against Tallmadge; family news, including Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman's pregnancy; and news on the religious revival as well as personal religious reflections.
    Tallmadge also expresses his indignation over Congress's handling of the case of Samuel Houston.
  - 1832 Jun-Jul (Folder 89)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman and Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman. The letters discuss family news, news of the religious revival, and an outbreak of cholera.
  - 1832 Aug-Dec (Folder 90)
    Four letters: three from Benjamin Tallmadge to the Cushmans, and one from Henry Floyd Tallmadge to his sister, Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman.
    Benjamin Tallmadge's letters mention financial matters; John Paine Cushman's illness; other family and social news; and Sarah Pierce's plan to select a female instructor for her school.
    Henry Floyd Tallmadge's letter requests that his sister send him "anti-billious" pills.
  - 1833 Jan-Feb (Folder 91)
    Three letters, from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge, discussing financial matters, including Martin Clapp; and his recent illness of jaundice and the illnesses of his wife and children.
  - 1833 Mar-May (Folder 92)
    Three letters, from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge, discussing financial matters; illnesses in the family; and plans for a trip to Litchfield.
  - 1833 Jun-Aug (Folder 93)
    Three letters, from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge, reporting on the death of Cushman's son William; offering religious reflections on death; and discussing financial matters.
  - 1833 Sep-Nov (Folder 94)
    Two letters: one from Henry Floyd Tallmadge to his sister, Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, and one from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge.
    The letter from Henry Floyd Tallmadge discusses the distressed situation of his sister in law, Laura.
    Cushman's letter to Tallmadge discusses a boat outing; the illness of his brother-in-law Delafield; and financial matters.
  - 1833 Dec (Folder 95)
    Five letters: one from Henry Floyd Tallmadge to his sister Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, and four from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge.
    Henry Floyd Tallmadge's letter reports on the illness of Benjamin Tallmadge and the treatment of his wound by the doctor. The letter begins with a note from Tallmadge's wife, Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge, on the same subject.
    Cushman's letters discuss financial matters, including mortgages and Tallmadge's debtor Martin Clapp; and thank Tallmadge for his recent financial gift to the Cushmans.
  - 1834 Jan-Mar (Folder 96)
    Three letters: one from Henry Floyd Tallmadge to his brother-in-law John Paine Cushman, and two from Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge.
    Henry Floyd Tallmadge's letter discusses how to dispose of the financial gift from Benjamin Tallmadge.
    Cushman's letters discuss financial matters, including a mention of Martin Clapp.
  - 1834 Apr-Dec (Folder 97)
    Two letters, from John Paine Cushman to Benjamin Tallmadge, discussing Tallmadge's financial dispute with Martin Clapp and sharing family news.
  - 1835 (Folder 98)
    One letter, from John Paine Cushman to his son E. F. Cushman, reporting on the death of Benjamin Tallmadge. Cushman also mentions Tallmadge's diary.
  - 1838 (Folder 99)
    Three letters: one from B. T. Cushman to his father John Paine Cushman, one from Henry Floyd Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, and one from Mary Pierce to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman.
    The letters report on the death of Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge and offer condolences.
  - 1839 (Folder 100)
    Letter, from Laura Tallmadge, the widow of George Washington Tallmadge, to her sister-in-law Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, discussing her upcoming marriage to Judge Humphrey.
  - 1844 (Folder 101)
    Two letters to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman: one from her brother Henry Floyd Tallmadge, and one from her sister-in-law, Maria. Both letters report on and lament the death of their son, Henry, who was drowned.
  - 1854 (Folder 102)
    Letter, from Frederick Augustus Tallmadge to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, reporting on the death of their brother Henry Floyd Tallmadge.
  - 1856 (Folder 103)
    Two letters, from Frederick Augustus Tallmadge to his sister Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, reporting on the death of their sister, Harriot (Tallmadge) Delafield.
  - n. d. (Folder 104)
    Three letters: one from Benjamin Tallmadge to his daughter Maria, and two anonymous letters.
    Tallmadge's letter, written when Maria was young, contains advice on grammar; criticizes Thomas Paine; and encourages Maria to teach "Ebo" to read.
    The two anonymous letters are addressed to "Officers of the Army" and exhort its listeners to argue for better treatment now that the Revolutionary War has been concluded.
- Legal papers, 1782-1844
  Series 2, arranged by type of material, consists of Tallmadge's legal documents. The majority of the papers concern land transactions, while others pertain to his store, Benjamin Tallmadge & Co., and to other financial investments. Also included in this series are bills of sale of slaves.
  - Bonds
    - 1790-1794 (Folder 1)
    - 1796-1823 (Folder 2)
  - Court documents
    - 1780, 1782 (Folder 1)
      Contains a copy of protest of a bill of exchange and the resolution of a debt.
    - 1793 (Folder 2)
      Contains a report by Benjamin Tallmadge and others on the mishandling of Revolutionary War funds by Jedediah Strong.
    - 1804 (Folder 3)
      Contains summons to Samuel Seymour, Caleb Bacon, Elnathan Holly and Hosea Blinn to appear before Frederick Wolcott, justice of the peace of Litchfield County, to testify in a suit brought by Benjamin Tallmadge against Reuben Webster.
    - 1844 (Folder 4)
      Contains printed pamphlet of a lawsuit between Henry Floyd Tallmadge and Henry A. Tallmadge, son of George Washington Tallmadge, concerning a bequest in the will of Benjamin Tallmadge.
  - Deeds
    - 1789 (Folder 1)
    - 1796 (Folder 2)
      Includes deeds to shares in the Ohio Company.
    - 1797-1799 (Folder 3)
    - 1814 (Folder 4)
  - Indentures (service)
    - 1785 (Folder 1)
      Contains indenture for Ebo, a "Mustee boy," by his mother.
    - 1788 (Folder 2)
      Contains indenture of a "Negro girl named Abigail" by Ruth Woodhull to Benjamin Tallmadge.
    - 1797 (Folder 3)
      Contains indenture of John Philip Monigati and his wife Margaratha as servants to Benjamin Tallmadge. Mentions that their term of service will extend six months for every child born to them during their term of service to Tallmadge.
  - Indentures (real estate)
    - 1784 (oversize) (Folder 1)
      See oversize
    - 1788-1789 (Folder 2)
    - 1799-1800 (Folder 3)
    - 1843 (Folder 4)
  - Leases
    - 1788-1789 (Folder 1)
    - 1791, 1795 (Folder 2)
  - Letters of attorney
    - 1778 (Folder 1)
      Contains document granting Benjamin Tallmadge power of attorney to transact business in shares in two privateering ships, the Mars and the Wooster.
    - 1784 (Folder 2)
    - 1788-1789 (Folder 3)
  - Obligations
    - 1782, 1786 (Folder 1)
      Contains agreements concerning Benjamin Tallmadge & Co. and a joint venture shipping horses to the West Indies.
    - 1791, 1792 (Folder 2)
  - Wills
    - 1838 (Folder 1)
      Contains drafts of the wills of Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge and Sarah Hallett.
  - Other contracts and agreements
    - 1780-1784 (Folder 1)
      Contains agreements related to the formation and finances of Benjamin Tallmadge & Co.
    - 1785-1787 (Folder 2)
      Contains agreements related to Benjamin Tallmadge & Co. and to land transactions.
    - 1788 (Folder 3)
      Contains documents concerning land transactions and a service contract between Benjamin Tallmadge and Cash Africa.
    - 1790-1791 (Folder 4)
      Contains documents concerning William Burrall's bankruptcy; a partnership between Benjamin Tallmadge and Julius Deming; and a lottery dispute.
    - 1793-1794 (Folder 5)
    - 1795 (Folder 6)
    - 1797 (Folder 7)
- Financial papers, 1778-1835
  Series 3, arranged by type of material, consists of Tallmadge's financial papers: accounts, account books, letterbooks, bills, and receipts.
  - Accounts
    - 1779-1789 (Folder 1)
      Contains accounts for the privateering brig Middletown.
    - 1813, 1820 (Folder 2)
      Contains list of lots in Ohio belonging to Benjamin Tallmadge.
    - 1821-1822 (Folder 3)
    - 1831 (Folder 4)
    - 1835 (Folder 5)
      Contains appraisal and inventory of Benjamin Tallmadge's estate.
    - n. d. (Folder 6)
    - n. d. (Folder 7)
    - Account book (oversize), 1788-1790
      Account book of Benjamin Tallmadge & Co. See oversize box (currently housed in 3B-Box 99).
    - Account book (oversize), 1805-1808
      Account book of Benjamin Tallmadge & Co. See oversize box (currently housed in 3B-Box 100).
    - Account book (oversize), 1807-1832
    - Letterbook (oversize), 1806-1811; 1856
      Letterbook of Tallmadge, Smith & Co., containing business letters and orders. See oversize box (currently housed in 3A-Box 19).
  - Bills and receipts
    - 1778 (Folder 1)
      Contains receipt for sale of share in the privateering brig Middletown.
    - 1779 Jan-Feb (Folder 2)
      Contains bills of interest on money borrowed by the United States.
    - 1779 Mar-May (Folder 3)
      Contains receipts related to the sale of shares in the privateering brig Middletown.
    - 1779 Jun-Jul (Folder 4)
    - 1779 Aug-Nov (Folder 5)
    - 1779 Dec (Folder 6)
    - 1780 (Folder 7)
    - 1781 (Folder 8)
      French payments for Wadsworth and Carter, members of Charles-René-Dominique Sochet, Chevalier Destouches' squadron.
    - 1783 (Folder 9)
      Includes bills for payment of wages and clothing during the American Revolution.
    - 1784 (Folder 10)
      Contains bill of sale for a slave named Prince to Benjamin Tallmadge.
    - 1785 (Folder 11)
    - 1787 (Folder 12)
      Includes contract documenting sale of a slave girl named Jane to Benjamin Tallmadge.
    - 1789 (Folder 13)
    - 1790 (Folder 14)
    - 1794 (Folder 15)
    - 1796 (Folder 16)
    - 1797 (Folder 17)
    - 1799 (Folder 18)
    - 1834 (Folder 19)
      Bill for board and tuition for Catherine Tallmadge.
    - undated (Folder 20)
      Includes inventory of cargo of the ship Nancy, taken as a prize by the ship Mars.
- Miscellany, 1783-1834
  Series 4, arranged chronologically, consists of Tallmadge's miscellaneous papers, which include numerous original poems; diplomas and certificates; and documents concerning Tallmadge's interest in pensions for army officers after the war.
  - Address to army, 1783 (Folder 1)
    Copy of George Washington's Newburgh Address.
  - Order passed by Congress, 1783 (Folder 2)
    Concerns payments to the army.
  - Resolutions, 1792 (Folder 3)
    Printed list of resolutions of a meeting of the Connecticut Proprietors in the Ohio Company's purchase.
  - Proceedings, 1795 (Folder 4)
    Pamphlet documenting proceedings of the state committee in the sale of the Western Reserve.
  - Land surveys, 1791, 1814 (Folder 5)